A Guide to the Papers of the American Association of University Women, Virginia Division, 1925-1981
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the American Association of University Women, Virginia Division 1925-1981
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6305, -a, -b, -c
This collection consists of 2,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited in the liabrary on 1960 May 28; 1979 Aug. 17; and, on 1983 Sept. 19. The collection was made a gift in 2008 following the dissolution of the Chapter in 2007.
Scope and Content
The papers contain state administrative files including minutes of the state board, executive committee, and annual conferences, president's papers, branch presidents' annual reports, resolutions and bylaws, national and division convention papers, division programs and bulletins, and branch bulletins, histories, and directories; topical files particularly for women's issues and education including the Virginia school desegregation controversy; and the Charlottesville branch files including bulletins, directories, by-laws, presidents' papers, publicity and financial material, and handbooks, histories and other pertinent printed material related to either the branches or topics of interest.
Contents List
- Series I: Administrative Files
  - Minutes of Executive Board and State Board 1929-1945, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Executive Board and State Board 1929-1945, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Minutes of State Board, Executive Board and Planning meeting 1948-1951 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of the Virginia State Conference of the AAUW 1926-1929, 1931-1936 (Box 1)
  - Minutes for the Conference of the Virginia Branch, AAUW 1937-1942, 1943-1951, (no Conference, 1945), (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Division minutes 1938-1954, 1952-1956, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Division minutes 1955-1957, 1957-1960, 1957-1962, 1960-1967, 1967-1969, (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Division President's Papers 1962-1969, 1974-1979, n. d., (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Annual Reports of Branch Presidents of the Virginia State Branch AAUW 1941-1942, 1943-1944, 1948-1949 (Box 3)
  - Division Resolutions 1965-1967, 1972-1978, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Division Bylaws 1975-1977 (Box 3)
  - National Conventions 1937, 1941, 1949, 1951, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Division Conventions 1950-1957, 1973-1979, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Division Convention programs 1958-1961 (Box 4)
  - Division Convention programs 1962-1965, 1966-1969, 1973-1975, 1979, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Division Legislative Programs 1972-1976, 1977-1978, 1979-1980, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Division Program Development 1973-1978, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Division workshops 1954-1963 (Box 4)
  - Division workshops 1963-1969 (Box 5)
  - Division bulletins 1931-1948, 1948-1955, 1955-1959, 1961-1976, (5 folders) (Box 5)
  - Division Branch bulletins 1976-1977, n.d. (Box 5)
  - AAUW Journal and AAUW Journal Newspaper1975 Jan - 1976 Nov (Box 5)
  - Branch Histories and Related Material 1926, 1959-1981 (Box 6)
  - Branches disbanded or under discussion for organization 1950-1969 (Box 6)
  - Branches organized 1967-1969 (Box 6)
  - Branche Presidents and Officers 1950 (Box 6)
  - Division membership 1974-1979 (Box 6)
  - Division Directories 1972-1977 (Box 6)
  - Division Corporate Representation 1973-1978, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Division Resources, Services and Supplies 1976-1978, n.d. (Box 6)
- Series II: Topical Files
  - Subseries A: Education
    - Education: Primary and Secondary 1926 Feb, 1949-1964, n.d. (Box 6)
    - Kindergartens in Virginia, Division Studies 1952 (Box 6)
    - Educational Foundation 1950, 1972-1980, n.d. (Box 6)
    - Integration in Virginia 1954-1956 (Box 7)
    - Building fund 1960-1961 (Box 7)
    - College Faculty Program (including information on recipient Elizabeth Warnick) 1964-1968 (Box 7)
    - Governor's Conference on Education 1966-1967 (Box 7)
    - Educational Foundation Certificates 1967-1976 (Box 7)
    - Coretta Scott King Educational Fund 1968-1969 (Box 7)
    - Education: "Back to Basics" 1977 Jul - 1978 Feb., n.d. (Box 7)
  - Subseries B: Miscellaneous
    - Investigation of Dorothy Kenyon by the Sub-Committee of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee 1950-1951 (Box 7)
    - South Atlantic Regional Conference 1960-1962, 1976, 1978, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Miller and Rhoads Woman's Forum 1962-1965 (Box 7)
    - Status of women 1964-1971 (Box 7)
    - International Women's Year 1972-1978, n.d. (Box 7)
    - International Federation of University Women 1974-1978 (Box 8)
    - The Twenty-first Century 1976-1980, n.d. (Box 8)
- Series III: Charlottesville Branch Files
  - "Constitution and Bylaws of the Charlottesville..." AAUW 1937 May (Box 8)
  - Charlottesville Branch: membership 1925, 1960-1964, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Programs from Productions 1934, 1948, 1950 (Box 8)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Bulletins 1949-1950, 1957-1969, 1971-1976, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Gilbert and Sullivan Productions 1957, 1973-1976 (Box 8)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Directories 1958-1978 (Box 8)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Bylaws and Procedures 1966-1975, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Contributions 1967-1979, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Charlottesville Branch: President's Papers 1972-1979, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Officers Lists 1973-1979, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Publicity 1973-1979, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Financial 1974-1979, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Public Issues Seminars 1977-1979, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Women as Agents of Change 1977-1978 (Box 9)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Women, Media, and the Law 1977, 1979 (Box 9)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Committee on Women Chairman's Papers 1979-1980, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Charlottesville Branch: Women's Coordinating Council 1979-1981, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Charlottesville Branch: "Mother Wit" script n.d. (Box 9)
- Series IV: Printed Material
  - The Daily Progress: Special Sections on "Women of Charlottesville" 1974 Oct 27, 1975 Oct 26, 1977 Oct 23, 1978 Oct 22, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - The Daily Progress: Special Sections on "Our Community and the Arts" 1974 Sep 24, 1976 Sep 21, 1977 Sep 20, 1978 Sep 19, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - The 1960-1970 Decade of the Va. Division of the AAUW Apr 1971 (Box 10)
  - The History of the Va. Division Jan 1960 (Box 10)
  - Your Questions, Our Answers about AAUW Area Reps Apr 1973 (Box 10)
  - Public Affairs Handbook 1971 (Box 10)
  - AAUW Legislative History and Policy Notes 1975-1977 Oct 1975 (Box 10)
  - AAUW Educational Foundation Programs 1976-1977 Awards and Grants Directory n.d. (Box 10)
  - AAUW Branch Leadership Handbook 1977 (Box 10)
  - Program Guide, 1979-1981 Feb 1979 (Box 10)
  - Social Services Directory Spring 1975 (Box 10)
  - A Long Range Plan for Library Development of the McIntyre Public Library Jun 1968 (Box 10)
  - Representatives Kit: AAUW Branch Representatives of the Areas of Interest May 1976 (Box 10)
  - The Status of Women in Winchester and Frederick County, Virginia: A Survey 1978 (Box 10)
  - Nuclear Debate: What's the Score? Oct 1976 (Box 10)
  - A Comprehensive Plan for Aging Services Oct 1974 (Box 10)
  - The Victim Advocate: A Special Criminal Justice Improvement Publication of the National District Attorney's Association 1978 (Box 10)
  - AAUW State Division Leaders Handbook Jun 1973 (Box 10)
  - Here to Stay by Mary Jo Bane, 1976, Basic Books, Inc., New York 1976, (2 copies) (Box 10)
  - Idealism at Work: AAUW Educational Foundation Programs, 1967-1981, by Doris C. Davies (AAUWEF: Billings, Montana) 1981 (Box 10)
  - The Proceedings of the Assembly on the Dimensions of Hunger and Malnutrition, eds., Jean DeVita Ethelyne Kristo, and Donald H. Smith n.d. (Box 11)
  - The Program Guide, AAUW 1979-1981 (Box 11)
  - "People Helping People: An Overview of Community Education" by Larry E. Decker (pamphlet) 1977 (Box 11)
  - "Public Schools: Use Them, Don't Waste Them" by Sylvia Porter, (ed. by Michael H. Kaplan) from Your Money's Worth--(pamphlet) 1975 (Box 11)
  - "Future Shock and You" by Anne W. Cheatham 1980 Jul (Box 11)